

# **Hunter Ratliff**

Nuclear Engineer and Code Developer

29 years old

🔁 Bergen, Norway

upon request available upon request

hratliff.com

contact@hratliff.com

in linkedin.com/in/hunter-ratliff

United States citizenship

## Skills -

Languages

EnglishJapanese

■ Norwegian

Programming

MATLAB

Git, GitHub

Nuclear / Scientific

MCNP6/X/5, PHITS • • • • • • ROOT

SCALE/ORIGEN • • • • •

Geant4 • • • •

Other

LaTeX, TikZ, MetaPost • • • • • Microsoft Office Suite • • • •

Windows local systems • • • •

Unix remote systems • • • •

HTML, CSS, Markdown • •

## **Summary**

Hunter is a nuclear engineer whose experience is predominantly with radiation transport simulations using MCNP and PHITS, activation and decay calculations, scientific code development in Python and Fortran, space radiation modeling, cosmic-ray-like ion accelerator experiments, and analysis and visualization of large experimental and modeled datasets. He also has interests in radiation protection and shielding, radiotherapy, and radioisotope production.

### **Experience**

Aug. 2021 – present

**Postdoctoral Fellow** Western Norway University of Applied Sciences (HVL) Development, modeling, analysis, and deployment of a prototype neutron/ $\gamma$ -ray detector that seeks to more precisely determine doses delivered in proton radiotherapy treatments to then allow for sparing of more healthy tissue surrounding the sites receiving treatment.

Apr. 2019 – Aug. 2021 **Postdoctoral Fellow**Japan Atomic Energy Agency (JAEA)
Member of the PHITS particle transport code team as the lead developer of the DCHAIN-PHITS activation, buildup, burnup, and decay

code coupled to PHITS. Implemented modern decay and cross section libraries, uncertainty propagation, reaction tracking, tetrahedral and 3-D grid mesh geometry support, performance improvements, new input/output features, and more into DCHAIN. Authored the user guide/manual and assisted with user support for DCHAIN-PHITS.

May 2015 – Feb. 2019 Graduate Research Assistant

Conducted accelerator experiments emulating radiation conditions within spacecraft, characterized resulting neutron spectra, and modeled the experiments in MCNP. Also modeled the Martian surface's radiation environment from galactic cosmic rays in MCNP and PHITS

and modernized the CLSQ Fortran IV decay analysis code in Python.

Aug. 2015 – Dec. 2016 **Graduate Teaching Assistant** The University of Tennessee, Knoxville Lead laboratory experience portions of courses within the Nuclear Engineering Department, further developing skills in troubleshooting radiation detectors and associated pulse chain equipment, teaching, communication, and providing constructive guidance to students.

#### **Education**

May 2015 – Dec. 2018 Grade: A (4.0/4.0) Ph.D. in Nuclear Engineering

Organized, conducted, and analyzed data from 400 hours of beam experiments at the NASA Space Radiation Laboratory in Brookhaven National Laboratory, characterizing the neutron environment within (emulated) spacecraft bombarded by cosmic rays using established time-of-flight and newly developed deconvolution techniques. This required substantial scripting to filter and process the raw data into spectra and to generate, run, and process MCNPX/6 models of the

experiment. Further detailed dose analyses were explored to draw

conclusions on optimal spacecraft shielding materials, thicknesses, and configurations to minimize risk to astronauts.

May 2015 – Dec. 2016 Grade: A (4.0/4.0) **M.S. in Nuclear Engineering**The University of Tennessee, Knoxville Designed and conducted MCNP6 simulations of the galactic cosmic ray-induced radiation environment on the Martian surface, modeling the individual particle spectra and dosimetric data as seen by the Radiation Assessment Detector onboard the Mars Curiosity Rover.

Aug. 2011 – May 2015 Grade: A (3.94/4.0) **B.S. in Nuclear Engineering** The University of Tennessee, Knoxville Designed a plate-fuel research reactor relevant to nuclear propulsion fuels testing and modeled its criticality and shielding in MCNP for a proposed critical experiment facility as a final design project.

# **Hunter Ratliff**

Nuclear Engineer and Code Developer

# **Specialties**

Programming and scripting

Monte Carlo methods/simulation

Data analysis and visualization

Documentation and presentation

Nuclear data processing/formatting

Web design/online tool development

## **Professional Bio**

Hunter studied for a BS in nuclear engineering at the University of Tennessee from 2011 to 2015 and, when presented with interesting space radiation research opportunities, continued with his graduate studies at UTK, earning a PhD in late 2018. Afterward, he moved to Japan in early 2019 to join the PHITS code development team at the Japan Atomic Energy Agency. In 2021 he then moved to Norway to work at Høgskulen på Vestlandet.

## Personal Bio -

After living his entire life in the US state of Tennessee, Hunter made his first trip abroad: moving to Japan. Since, he has thoroughly enjoyed exploring the local scenery, culture, and language everywhere he has lived. New experiences in travel, cuisine, and forces of nature have truly opened his eyes to the staggering variety of experiences the world has to offer. He is enthusiastic about learning other languages and cultures on his nowinternational journey through life.

## Other -



American Nuclear Society member

Tennessee Class D driver's license

Eagle Scout, Boy Scouts of America

Degrees, certificates, and any other documents available upon request

#### **Publications**

2022 Development of scalable deconvolution methods for determining secondary target neutron yields from dual-thick-target cosmicray ion accelerator experiments

> H.N. Ratliff, N.A. McGirl, M.R. Beach, L.A. Castellanos, M.S. Clowdsley, L.H. Heilbronn, C. La Tessa, J.W. Norbury, A. Rusek, M. Sivertz, A.P. Srikrishna, H. Wang, and C. Zeitlin

Nucl. Instrum. Methods Phys. Res., B, (in internal review)

2022 Double-differential primary target neutron yields from dual-thicktarget proton and heavy ion accelerator experiments

> H.N. Ratliff, N.A. McGirl, M.R. Beach, L.A. Castellanos, M.S. Clowdsley, L.H. Heilbronn, C. La Tessa, J.W. Norbury, A. Rusek, M. Sivertz, A.P. Srikrishna, H. Wang, and C. Zeitlin

Nucl. Instrum. Methods Phys. Res., B, (in internal review)

Modernization of the DCHAIN-PHITS activation code with new fea-2020 tures and updated data libraries

H.N. Ratliff, N. Matsuda, S. Abe, T. Miura, T. Furuta, Y. Iwamoto, T. Sato

Nucl. Instrum. Methods Phys. Res., B, 484, 29-41, Dec. 2020.

Secondary neutron yields from thick-target GCR accelerator ex-2018 periments

> H.N. Ratliff, N.A. McGirl, L.A. Castellanos, H. Wang, A.P. Srikrishna, and L.H. Heilbronn

> Proceedings of 20th Topical Meeting of the Radiation Protection and

Shielding Division of the American Nuclear Society

2018 Light charged ion measurements and Monte Carlo calculations

from thick targets bombarded by protons and heavy ions

H. Wang, L.A. Castellanos, N.A. McGirl, <u>H.N. Ratliff</u>, A.P. Srikrishna, and L.H. Heilbronn

Proceedings of 20th Topical Meeting of the Radiation Protection and

Shielding Division of the American Nuclear Society

2017 Simulation of the GCR spectrum in the Mars Curiosity Rover's RAD

detector using MCNP6

H.N. Ratliff, M.B.R. Smith, and L.H. Heilbronn

Life Sciences in Space Research, 14, Suppl. C, 43-50, Jun. 2017.

2017 The radiation environment on the surface of Mars - Summary of

model calculations and comparison to RAD data

D. Matthiä, D.M. Hassler, W. de Wet, B. Ehresmann, A. Firan, J. Flores-McLaughlin, J. Guo, L.H. Heilbronn, K. Lee, H.N. Ratliff, R.R. Rios, T. Slaba, M.B.R. Smith, L.W. Townsend, T. Berger, G. Reitz, R.F. Wimmer-Schweingruber, and C. Zeitlin

Life Sciences in Space Research, 14, Suppl. C, 18–28, Jun. 2017.

### **Honors and Awards**

2015 – 2018	Chancellor's Distinguished Graduate Fellowship	Univ. of Tennessee
2011 – 2015	Chancellor's Honors Program	Univ. of Tennessee
2013 – 2014	Eastland Family Engineering Scholarship	
2013	US Nuclear Regulatory Commission Scholarship	
2012 – 2013	Energy Solutions Corporation Engineering Scholarsh	nip

Tennessee Society of Professional Engineers Scholarship

# References

2011 – 2012

available upon request